# Alan Guedes — C.V.

London – UK

■ a.guedes@ucl.ac.uk • • alanlivio.github.io • in alanlivio • ■ alanlivio • ■ alanlivio • ■ alanlivio

## Shorbio

I am a Computer Scientist (PhD & Postdoc) interested in geometric Machine Learning (ML) for the next generation of immersive systems and graph-based data. My career can be seen threefold. In research, I worked on research Multimedia & ML projects, contributed to communities (Springer, ACM SIGMM and SBC WebMedia), and have been awarded research funding. In teaching, I co-supervised students, acted as a lecturer on under- and post-graduate courses, and organized workshops to promote student interest in public engagement. Last, I added value to the industry through open source and standards in TV forums (ITU-T SG16 and BR TV Forum).

# **Experiences**

Work.....

#### UCL, LASP Lab

Postdoc Researcher on ML project

2021-today

Highlights: ACM SIGMM committees and workshop organizer; co-supervised undergrad students.

- SpheryStream project funded by EPSRC to Improve 360-video streaming with profile-based methods

#### PUC-Rio. TeleMidia Lab

Postdoc Researcher on ML & Multimedia projects

2017-2020

Highlights: project PI; team leader; standards contributions; SBC WebMedia committees and workshop organizer (students for social impact); co-supervised under/postgrad students; postgraduate lecturer assistant.

- VideoMR project, funded by Microsoft & RNP to detect inappropriate content in video scenes;
- AML (Anti-Money Laundry) project funded by BTG Bank to detect financial transctions risk and anomaly detection;
- GT-RAP project funded by RNP to develop a blockchain-based system for academic certificates.

### Dynavideo, TV Division

Software engineer

2012-2012

Highlights: multiple awarded social impact project.

- Brasil4D project funded by World Bank to transmit interactive TV content with social features to low-income families. Its results were published in a public report

Education

#### **PUC-Rio**

PhD. in Informatics. Thesis on Multimodal-multiuser support in multimedia scene descriptions 2013–2017 Highlights: thesis concepts used in SBTVD standard; industry committees.

- PUC-Rio Ginga reference implementation, funded by PUC-Rio Software Licenses to TV manufacturers;
- From SBTVD Conformance Test Suite for TV manufacturers

#### **UFPB**

MSc. in Informatics. Thesis on Multi-device support in TV app stores

2010-2012

Highlights: thesis concepts used in the awarded Brasil4D project; undergraduate lecturer; project leader

- GingaAppStore, funded by RNP, to design a broadband system to deliver TV applications;
- Art TVDI, funded by RNP, to design agile methods for TV applications development;

#### **UFPB**

BSc. in Computer Science. Final report on Component-based architecture for TV middleware

2005-2009

- Ginga CDN, funded by RNP, to develop reusable TV middleware components.
- Tutor on Analysis and design of Algorithms;
- Part-Time software developer at Dynavideo TV Division to prototype TV software in ST boards.

## Research

Publications...

Google Scholar shows >40 published papers, >100 citations, h-index 6. See below recent and some selected publications.

Elsevier Book Chapter	2022
ACM Multimedia Systems.	2022 2022
•	2016, 2020
IEEE Symposium on Multimedia (ISM).	2020
SBC WebMedia 2020, 2020, 2020, 2021, 2	
ACM Symposium on Document Engineering.	2019
IEEE Multimedia Signal Processing.	2019
Committees	
ACM, Special Interest Group on Multimedia	
	2020-today
- Multimedia conference: reviewer (2022), area chair (2022), reproducibility chair (2023)	•
- Multimedia Systems (ACM MM): MMVE review (2021, 2022, 2023) and demo chair (2022) - Immersive Experiences (ACM IMX) conference: reviewer (2022) and area chair (2022)	
- QoMex conference (ACM QoMEX): reviewer (2023)	
BR Computing Society (SBC), Web&Mulimedia Commitee	
Steering Committee	2021-today
	2017-today
- WebMedia conference reviewer (2017-today), chair of Undergrad workshop (2018), chair of Demos (2019-2022), and chair of Social Impact Workshop (2019-2022)	; Workshop
Springer Reviewer	2022-today
- Journal of Multimedia Tools and Applications: reviewer (2022, 2023)	2022-10Uay
- Iberoamerican Conference on TV Applications and Usability: reviewer (2020, 2021, 2022)	
Brazilian TV Forum (SBTVD)	
8	2017-2021
International Telecommunication Union (ITU)  Academic member at $SG-16/Q13$ contributing to IPTV middleware standards	2017-2021
Teaching	
reaching	
UCL	
UCL	2022-today
UCL Co-supervise undergrad engineering projects. SBC WebMedia	Š
UCL Co-supervise undergrad engineering projects. SBC WebMedia Organizer of students workshop to promote Social Impact research.	2022-today 2018-2022
UCL Co-supervise undergrad engineering projects. SBC WebMedia Organizer of students workshop to promote Social Impact research. PUC-Rio	2018-2022
UCL Co-supervise undergrad engineering projects.  SBC WebMedia Organizer of students workshop to promote Social Impact research.  PUC-Rio Invited Lecture on ML for Multimedia to postgrad students (>30)	2018-2022 2019
UCL Co-supervise undergrad engineering projects.  SBC WebMedia Organizer of students workshop to promote Social Impact research.  PUC-Rio Invited Lecture on ML for Multimedia to postgrad students (>30) Lecturer on TV development to undergrad students (>30).	2018-2022
UCL Co-supervise undergrad engineering projects.  SBC WebMedia Organizer of students workshop to promote Social Impact research.  PUC-Rio Invited Lecture on ML for Multimedia to postgrad students (>30)	2018-2022 2019 2013
UCL Co-supervise undergrad engineering projects.  SBC WebMedia Organizer of students workshop to promote Social Impact research.  PUC-Rio Invited Lecture on ML for Multimedia to postgrad students (>30) Lecturer on TV development to undergrad students (>30).  Japan International Cooperation Agency	2018-2022 2019 2013
UCL Co-supervise undergrad engineering projects.  SBC WebMedia Organizer of students workshop to promote Social Impact research.  PUC-Rio Invited Lecture on ML for Multimedia to postgrad students (>30) Lecturer on TV development to undergrad students (>30).  Japan International Cooperation Agency Lecturer and course design on TV development to South American countries professionals (>30)  RNP ESR	2018-2022 2019 2013 2012
UCL Co-supervise undergrad engineering projects.  SBC WebMedia Organizer of students workshop to promote Social Impact research.  PUC-Rio Invited Lecture on ML for Multimedia to postgrad students (>30) Lecturer on TV development to undergrad students (>30).  Japan International Cooperation Agency Lecturer and course design on TV development to South American countries professionals (>30)  RNP ESR Lecturer on Linux Administration to IT professionals (>30)	2018-2022 2019 2013 2012 2011
UCL Co-supervise undergrad engineering projects.  SBC WebMedia Organizer of students workshop to promote Social Impact research.  PUC-Rio Invited Lecture on ML for Multimedia to postgrad students (>30) Lecturer on TV development to undergrad students (>30).  Japan International Cooperation Agency Lecturer and course design on TV development to South American countries professionals (>30)  RNP ESR Lecturer on Linux Administration to IT professionals (>30)  UFPB Lecturer and course design on Programming Introduction (C language) to undergrad students (>Funding & Awards	2018-2022 2019 2013 2012 2011
Co-supervise undergrad engineering projects.  SBC WebMedia Organizer of students workshop to promote Social Impact research.  PUC-Rio Invited Lecture on ML for Multimedia to postgrad students (>30) Lecturer on TV development to undergrad students (>30).  Japan International Cooperation Agency Lecturer and course design on TV development to South American countries professionals (>30)  RNP ESR Lecturer on Linux Administration to IT professionals (>30)  UFPB Lecturer and course design on Programming Introduction (C language) to undergrad students (>	2018-2022 2019 2013 2012 2011
UCL Co-supervise undergrad engineering projects.  SBC WebMedia Organizer of students workshop to promote Social Impact research.  PUC-Rio Invited Lecture on ML for Multimedia to postgrad students (>30) Lecturer on TV development to undergrad students (>30).  Japan International Cooperation Agency Lecturer and course design on TV development to South American countries professionals (>30)  RNP ESR Lecturer on Linux Administration to IT professionals (>30)  UFPB Lecturer and course design on Programming Introduction (C language) to undergrad students (>Funding & Awards  Microsoft&RNP	2018-2022 2019 2013 2012 2011 
UCL Co-supervise undergrad engineering projects.  SBC WebMedia Organizer of students workshop to promote Social Impact research.  PUC-Rio Invited Lecture on ML for Multimedia to postgrad students (>30) Lecturer on TV development to undergrad students (>30).  Japan International Cooperation Agency Lecturer and course design on TV development to South American countries professionals (>30)  RNP ESR Lecturer on Linux Administration to IT professionals (>30)  UFPB Lecturer and course design on Programming Introduction (C language) to undergrad students (> Funding & Awards  Microsoft&RNP Approved as PI in VideoMR project	2018-2022 2019 2013 2012 2011 
UCL Co-supervise undergrad engineering projects.  SBC WebMedia Organizer of students workshop to promote Social Impact research.  PUC-Rio Invited Lecture on ML for Multimedia to postgrad students (>30) Lecturer on TV development to undergrad students (>30).  Japan International Cooperation Agency Lecturer and course design on TV development to South American countries professionals (>30)  RNP ESR Lecturer on Linux Administration to IT professionals (>30)  UFPB Lecturer and course design on Programming Introduction (C language) to undergrad students (> Funding & Awards  Microsoft&RNP Approved as PI in VideoMR project  ACM	2018-2022 2019 2013 2012 2011 -15) 2010 2019

Multiple TV associations	
FRIDA Innovative TV technological solutions award for Brasil4D project	2014
SET Conference award on Best TV interactivity solution for Brasil4D project	2013
PremioTV on Innovation and Creativity for Brasil4D project	2013
ITU	
IPTV Application Challenge User-friendliness for GingaStore	2012
Skills	
Academic: Execute research agenda. Scientific and standard writting.	
Teaching: Course design. Presentation skills.	
Programing: Python, TensorFlow, Bash, C++, Lua, Java, JavaScript, Latex, Docke	er.
Social: Good and empathic communication. Positive, make-it-happen, teamwork, lea	id-by-example attitudes.
Languages: Portuguese (mother tongue), English (fluent), and Spanish (fluent).	
Training	
UCL	
Data Protection for Researchers; Fundamentals in Research Funding.	2022-2023
Nature	
Interpreting Scientific Results; Focus on Peer Review.	2022-2023

# References

ITU

- Laura Toni, I.toni@ucl.ac.uk. Postdoc supervisor at UCL.

ITU-T A.1: Working Methods of ITU-T Study Groups

- Simone DJ Barbosa, simone@inf.puc-rio.br. PhD supervisor at PUC-Rio.
- Marcelo Moreno, moreno@ice.ufjf.br. ITU SG-16/Q13 and SBTVD collaborator.
- $\ Roberto \ Azevedo, \ roberto. azevedo @disneyresearch.com. \ Tele Midia \ collaborator.$

2023